PLOS ONE







                                                      RESEARCH ARTICLE


                                                      The medicinal mushroom Ganoderma lucidum


                                                      attenuates UV-induced skin carcinogenesis


                                                      and immunosuppression



                                                      Ayaz Shahid 1*, Matthew Huang1, Mandy Liu1, Md Abdullah Shamim 1, Cyrus Parsa2,3, 
                                                      Robert Orlando2,3, Ying Huang1 *


                                                      1 Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, College of Pharmacy, Western University of Health Sciences, 
                                                      Pomona, California, United States of America, 2 College of Osteopathic Medicine of the Pacific, Western 
                                                      University of Health Sciences, Pomona, California, United States of America, 3 Department of Pathology, 
                                                      Beverly Hospital, Montebello, California, United States of America


                                                      * ashahid@westernu.edu (AS); yhuang@westernu.edu (YH)





                                                      Abstract


                                                      The medicinal mushroom Ganoderma lucidum is traditionally used for treating multiple dis- 

    OPEN ACCESS                                       eases, including cancer. This study examined skin cancer preventive activity of a commer- 
                                                      cial product containing spore and fruiting body in 30:8 ratio (GLSF). Extracts of GLSF and 
Citation: Shahid A, Huang M, Liu M, Shamim MA, 
Parsa C, Orlando R, et al. (2022) The medicinal       spore component (GLS) were prepared using artificial gastrointestinal juice and examined 
mushroom Ganoderma lucidum attenuates UV-             on JB6 cells. GLSF and GLS dose-dependently inhibited epidermal growth factor-induced 

induced skin carcinogenesis and                       JB6 transformation at non-toxic concentrations. SKH-1 mice which were fed with diets con- 
immunosuppression. PLoS ONE 17(3): e0265615.          taining GLSF (1.25%), GLS (0.99%) or the fruiting body (GLF) (0.26%) were exposed to 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0265615
                                                      chronic low-dose ultraviolet (UV) radiation to assess their effects on skin carcinogenesis. 
Editor: N. Rajendra Prasad, Annamalai University,     GLSF, but not GLS or GLF, reduced skin tumor incidence and multiplicity. In non-tumor skin 
INDIA
                                                      tissues of mice, GLSF attenuated UV-induced epidermal thickening, expression of Ki-67, 
Received: July 30, 2021                               COX-2 and NF-κB, while in tumor tissues, GLSF increased expression of CD8 and Gran- 
Accepted: March 1, 2022                               zyme B. To examine the effects of GLSF on UV-induced immunosuppression, mice which 

Published: March 21, 2022                             were fed with GLSF were evaluated for the contact hypersensitivity (CHS) response to dini- 

Copyright: © 2022 Shahid et al. This is an open       trofluorobenzene (DNFB). GLSF significantly reversed UV-mediated suppression of DNFB- 
access article distributed under the terms of the     induced CHS by increasing CD8+ and decreasing CD4+ and FoxP3+ T-cells in mouse ears. 

Creative Commons Attribution License, which           Therefore, GLSF prevents skin cancer probably via attenuating UV-induced 
permits unrestricted use, distribution, and           immunosuppression.
reproduction in any medium, provided the original 
author and source are credited.

Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are 
within the paper and its Supporting information 
files.

Funding: Research reported in the publication was     Introduction
partly supported by Beijing Tong Ren Tang Chinese     Skin cancer is a major type of cancer with a well-known association with environmental fac- 
Medicine Co., Ltd. This work was also supported       tor–solar ultraviolet (UV) radiation. Overexposure to UV radiation, particularly in the mid- 
by Western University of Health Sciences              wavelength range (UVB, 280–320 nm), is the most significant risk factor for the development 
Intramural Student Funds as part of the Graduate 
Program. The funders had no role in study design,     of non-melanoma skin cancers (NMSC), including basal cell and squamous cell carcinomas 
data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or (BCC and SCC), which originate from keratinocytes. In contrast to many other tumor types, 

preparation of the manuscript.                        NMSC incidence is increasing at an alarming rate in the US—3 to 4 million cases of BCC and






PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0265615 March 21, 2022                                                                                                     1 / 18

PLOS ONE                                                                     Ganoderma lucidum prevent UV-induced skin cancer and immunosuppression


Competing interests: The authors have declared 1 million cases of SCC annually [1–3]. Chemoprevention, i.e., using a pharmacological 
that no competing interests exist.             approach to block or reverse the initiation, promotion and progression of cancer, represents a 
                                               very attractive strategy for the control of NMSC.
                                                  UV radiation not only induces DNA damage and skin inflammation, but also creates an 
                                               immunosuppressive microenvironment in which premalignant cells are able to grow into 
                                               tumors [4]. Only when mutations and immunosuppression coexist, it is possible for skin 
                                               tumors to occur [5]. Supporting this notion, organ transplant recipients who receive long- 
                                               term immunosuppressant treatment are at increased risk for skin cancer [6]: for BCC, there is 
                                               a 10-fold increased risk in organ transplant recipients, while the risk of developing SCC is 
                                               increased by 65–250 times. UV-irradiated skin is unable to elicit sensitization to contact aller- 
                                               gens by development of immune tolerance to them [7]. UV-irradiated skin is also unable to 
                                               reject syngeneic UV-induced tumors, although the same tumors are strongly rejected when 
                                               transplanted into non-UV-exposed syngeneic mice [8]. Therefore, overcoming UV-induced 
                                               immunosuppression could be an important strategy for skin cancer prevention.
                                                  Since the target population for cancer chemoprevention is healthy individuals, pharmaco- 
                                               logical agents that can be used for the preventive purposes should be both effective and safe. 
                                               Therefore, natural products have become a very attractive source for developing cancer pre- 
                                               ventive agents. Ganoderma lucidum (GL), commonly known as Reishi or Lingzhi, is a medici- 
                                               nal mushroom recorded in the American Herbal Pharmacopoeia (2000) as one of the most 
                                               popular and highly effective herbal medicines and is frequently used as an ingredient in dietary 
                                               supplements. It has been used for thousands of years for the prevention and treatment of 
                                               many diseases due to a wide spectrum of actions, including immunomodulatory, anti-inflam- 
                                               matory, antioxidant, and antitumor properties [9]. The most important and widely studied 
                                               pharmacologically active compounds in GL are polysaccharides and triterpenoids [10, 11].
                                                  The present study examined the chemopreventive efficacy and potential mechanisms for 
                                               GL on skin carcinogenesis. GLS and GLF are commercial products derived from the broken 
                                               spore or fruiting body of GL, respectively. GLSF is a relatively new GLS-derived product con- 
                                               taining GLS and GLF in a 30:8 ratio. The present study demonstrated that GLSF has skin can- 
                                               cer chemopreventive activity both in vitro and in vivo. In a chronic UV induced skin 
                                               carcinogenesis mouse model, GLSF, but not GLS or GLF, prevented UV-induced skin carcino- 
                                               genesis in-vivo. To explore a possible mechanism of GLSF’s anticancer effects, an established 
                                               model of contact hypersensitivity (CHS) in mice was used to evaluate the effects of the dietary 
                                               GLSF on the immunosuppressive effects of UV. These results led us to conclude that this spe- 
                                               cific product derived from GL containing both spore and fruiting body may have a novel func- 
                                               tion in skin cancer prevention. Although this study used murine skin carcinogenesis models, 
                                               these data may support further clinical investigations of GLSF on other types of cancer.

                                               Materials and methods 
                                               Preparation of GLSF extracts
                                               A single batch of a commercial product manufactured by Beijing Tong Ren Tang Chinese 
                                               Medicine Co. (Hong Kong, China), named as GLSF, containing a mixture of the spore (GLS) 
                                               and fruiting body of GL (GLF) (30:8 ratio in weight), was used throughout the present study. 
                                               The artificial gastrointestinal juice was prepared according to reported methods [12, 13]. In 
                                               brief, the gastric extracts were prepared by mixing 5 grams of GLSF or GLS powder in 50 mL 
                                               of artificial gastric juice in 37˚C shaker for 1 hour, then 50 mL of artificial intestinal juice was 
                                               added and incubated at 37˚C shaker for additional 5 hours. The mixture was centrifuged at 
                                               room temperature for 15 minutes at 4,700 g, and the supernatant was collected. The solution 
                                               was then neutralized to pH 7.0 using 0.2 N NaOH. The extract was filtered using Whatman



PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0265615 March 21, 2022                                                                             2 / 18

PLOS ONE                             Ganoderma lucidum prevent UV-induced skin cancer and immunosuppression


                      filter paper No. 42, lyophilized, and stored at -20˚C. An established HPLC-DAD fingerprint 
                      method based on 11 chemical markers has been used for identity determination of GLSF, GLS, 
                      and GLF [14].

                      Cell line and cell culture
                      The JB6 CI 41-5a (also named JB6 P+) is a mouse epidermal cell line purchased from Ameri- 
                      can Type Culture Collection (ATCC, Manassas, VA) sensitive to promotion by growth factors 
                      or environmental stressors, including EGF. The JB6 P+ cells were cultured in Eagle’s mini- 
                      mum essential medium (EMEM) containing 4% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum and 1% 
                      penicillin/streptomycin and incubated at 37˚C in 5% CO2/95% air.

                      UV light source
                      UV lamps emitting UVC (100–280 nm; 2% of total energy), UVA (320–400 nm; 37% of total 
                      energy), UVB (280–320 nm; 54% of total energy), and visible light (400–450 nm; 7% of total 
                      energy; catalog nos., #95-0042-08 and #95-0043-13, UVP) were used to irradiate in both in 
                      vitro and in vivo experiments. UVX Radiometer (#97-0015-02, UVP) coupled with a sensor 
                      with a calibration point of 310 nm (UVX-31, #97-0016-04, UVP) was used to measure stable 
                      power output (mW/cm2). The exposure time was determined using the following formula: 
                      dose (mJ/cm2) = exposure time (s)*output intensity (mW/cm2). Quality control of the lamps 
                      and exposure time were calculated and monitored before using each of the lamps to account 
                      for power output changes.

                      JB6 anchorage independent soft-agar assay
                      The JB6 P+ cell line (neonatal BALB/c epidermal cells) is sensitive to transformation. The soft 
                      agar assay supports cells to grow in 3-dimension, mimicking in vivo cell growth. The process 
                      of this assay has been described previously [15]. In brief, In a 96-well tissue culture plate, 2x103 
                      JB6 P+ cells were mixed with 0.33% agar and suspended on top of a solidified bottom layer 
                      containing 0.5% agar. Nobel Agar (Sigma-Aldrich) was prepared in PBS, autoclaved, and 
                      stored at 4˚C. EGF (10 ng/mL) was used to promote and stimulate the anchorage-independent 
                      growth of JB6 P+ cells. The GLSF or GLS extracts were mixed with EGF and added to both 
                      agar layers. Plates were incubated at 37˚C with 5% CO2/95% air for 10–14 days. Colonies 
                      larger than 10 cells were counted manually under a microscope. The anchorage-independent 
                      soft agar assay can be used to identify chemopreventive activities of GLSF or GLS extracts by 
                      accessing their ability to suppress cell transformation of JB6 P+ induced by EGF.

                      Cell proliferation assay
                      96-well plates were seeded with 3,000 to 4,000 cells per well and allowed to attach overnight. 
                      Cells were treated with test compounds for 72 hours and incubated at 37˚C in 5% CO2/95% 
                      air. According to the manufacturer’s protocol, cell viability was determined using Sulforhoda- 
                      mine B (SRB) assay (Sigma) according to manufacturer’s protocol.

                      Rodent dietary supplement of GLS, GLF, and GLSF
                      To evaluate the cancer preventive effects of GLSF in comparison with GLS and GLF in vivo, 
                      the test agents were homogeneously blended into the AIN 93G diet by Animal Specialties 
                      (Hubbard, OR). The formulations included 1.25% GLSF, 0.26% GLF, or 0.99% GLS. The drug 
                      dose calculation was based on an average daily intake of 4 grams per mouse. Food


PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0265615 March 21, 2022 3 / 18

PLOS ONE                             Ganoderma lucidum prevent UV-induced skin cancer and immunosuppression


                      consumption for each group was monitored weekly during the course of the study and con- 
                      firmed that the dose of GLSF, GLF and GLS was approximately 2.0 g/kg, 0.42 and 1.58 g/kg, 
                      respectively.

                      Skin carcinogenesis studies in mice
                      All animal studies were carried out in accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for 
                      the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health and approved by 
                      the Western University of Health Sciences Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee 
                      (Pomona, CA). Five-week-old female SKH-1 mice (Charles River, Wilmington, MA) were ran- 
                      domly divided into five groups (n = 12). For a diet-based drug regimen study, Groups 1 and 2 
                      were fed with the standard diet AIN 93G, while groups 3, 4 and 5 were fed with diet containing 
                      GLS, GLF and GLSF. Mice were switched to modified diet 1 week after arrival. 4 weeks after 
                      starting the modified diet, the mice were irradiated with gradually increasing levels of UV 
                      three times a week for 27 weeks with an initial dose of 50 mJ/cm2that is increased each week 
                      by 25 mJ/cm2to 150 mJ/cm2, which is continued for the duration of the experiment. During 
                      the UV exposure, mice roamed freely in acrylic cages on a rotating platform with rotational 
                      placement ensuring consistent and equal dorsal distribution of UV irradiation. Tumors of at 
                      least 1 mm in diameter were counted and measured with a caliper weekly. The tumor volume 
                      was calculated according to the formula: (width)2x length/2. At the end of the study, animals 
                      were anesthetized with isoflurane until respiration ceased, and all efforts were made to mini- 
                      mize suffering. Tumorous and non-tumorous skin samples were excised and fixed in 10% for- 
                      malin for pathological analysis.

                      Contact hypersensitivity (CHS) assay
                      The UV radiation-induced suppression of the immune system in mice was assessed using the 
                      CHS model, as described previously [16]. In brief, the SKH-1 hairless mice (females) from the 
                      breeding cohort were randomly distributed into 5 groups (6–8 weeks). The mice were pre- 
                      treated with a modified diet containing GLS, GLF, GLSF or control diet for 4 weeks. Mice 
                      were irradiated with a single dose of UV (336 mJ/cm2) on the back. During exposure, the ear 
                      skin of mice is protected by covering with black electric tape. 24 hours after UV exposure, the 
                      mice were sensitized with freshly prepared 2,4-dinitro-1-fluorobenzene (DNFB) (Sigma) (25 
                      uL, 0.5% in acetone:olive oil 4:1, vol/vol) on UV treated back skin. Seven days later, the mice 
                      were challenged with DNFB (10 ul, 0.5%) on the right ear skin (dorsal side only) (the other ear 
                      treated with vehicle). 24 hours after the challenge, the mice were euthanized and 5 mm punch 
                      biopsies were obtained from the ears and weighed before fixation in 10% formalin. Previous 
                      studies have demonstrated that measurement of weights of ear punch biopsies correlated with 
                      measurement of ear thickness with calipers [16]. We prefer this method due to greater repro- 
                      ducibility in our data. Non-UV irradiated mice that received the same dose of DNFB serves as 
                      a positive control. Non-UV-irradiated mice that received only ear challenge serve as a negative 
                      control.

                      Histopathological analysis and immunohistochemical staining for 
                      detection of NF-kB, COX-2, Ki-67, CD8, CD4, Granzyme B, and FoxP3
                      For the carcinogenesis study, the non-tumorous and tumorous skin tissues, and the CHS 
                      study, the ears were excised, and all the tissues were fixed in 10% neutral formalin and embed- 
                      ded in paraffin. The paraffin-embedded tissues were then de-paraffinized using xylene and 
                      ethanol. To analyze histology, the de-paraffinized sections were stained with hematoxylin and 
                      eosin (H&E). In IHC, for antigen retrieval, sections were boiled in antigen retrieval Buffer (cat


PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0265615 March 21, 2022 4 / 18

PLOS ONE                             Ganoderma lucidum prevent UV-induced skin cancer and immunosuppression


                      no. ab93678) for 20 minutes. Different expression of proteins in skin tissue was determined 
                      using the Vectastain Elite ABC universal plus kit (PK-8200). In brief, sections were incubated 
                      with bloxall endogenous enzyme blocking solution for 10 min to quenching of endogenous 
                      peroxidase activity and then rinsed three times (5 min each) with TBST (0.05% Tween-20). 
                      Blocking solution was applied for 20 minutes; then sections were incubated with diluted poly- 
                      clonal antibodies, anti-COX-2 (1:200, Cell Signaling Technology), anti- NF-kB (p65) (1:400, 
                      Cell Signaling Technology), Ki-67 (1:400, Cell Signaling Technology), CD8 (1:400, Cell Signal- 
                      ing Technology), CD4 (1:100, Cell Signaling Technology), Granzyme B (1:125, Cell Signaling 
                      Technology) and FoxP3 (1:400, Cell Signaling Technology) overnight at 4˚C in a humid cham- 
                      ber [For more information about antibodies see S1 Table]. Further processing was performed 
                      according to the instructions of the Detection System. Scoring the images from IHC analysis 
                      was carried out using a semi-quantitative scoring system. Ki-67 was scored by counting the 
                      positively stained cells in 4 to 5 fields at various locations along the skin section to obtain the 
                      average for each mouse skin (n = 3 mice for long-term UV study). To quantitate CD8, CD4, 
                      Granzyme B, FoxP3 COX-2, and NF-kB staining, an expression index was calculated by the 
                      extent of staining multiplied by the intensity of staining. For the extent of staining, the follow- 
                      ing system was used: 0, no staining, 1 is < 25% of cells positive, 2 is >25% and <50% of cells 
                      positive, and 3 is >50% of cells positive. For staining intensity, the following system was used: 
                      0 is no staining, 1 is faint staining, 2 is moderate staining, and 3 is strong staining. Skin sections 
                      were evaluated at 20x or 40x magnification using a Leica DM750 LED Biological Microscope.


                      Statistical analysis
                      Data are expressed as mean +/- standard error or standard deviation and was analyzed using 
                      GraphPad Prism software. One-way ANOVA analysis with Dunnett’s multiple comparison 
                      test or student t test was used. For all statistical analysis, mean was indicated to be statistically 
                      different when P < 0.05.


                      Results
                      Effects of GLSF and GLS extracts on EGF-induced neoplastic 
                      transformation of JB6 P+ cells
                      Since signaling through EGF and its receptor EGFR promotes skin cancer, EGF was used to 
                      promote the transformation of mouse epidermal cells JB6 P+ (the tumor promoter sensitive 
                      subline). EGF (10 ng/mL) consistently induced anchorage-independent colony formation as 
                      expected [17]. As the colony formation in soft agar is dependent on cell viability, we first con- 
                      ducted a SRB cytotoxicity assay in JB6 P+ cells growing in a monolayer to evaluate the effects 
                      of these extracts on growth inhibition for this specific cell type. The GLSF and GLS extracts 
                      showed comparable in vitro effects on cell proliferation. For both extracts, SRB assay showed 
                      dose-dependent growth inhibitory activity (IC50was estimated as 1.0 mg/mL) (Fig 1A and 
                      1B). Next, the extracts at the dose range of 0.004 to 1.0 mg/mL were examined on EGF-
                      induced JB6 P+ cell transformation. The data showed that both GLSF and GLS inhibited trans- 
                      formation (i.e., soft agar colony formation) in a dose-dependent manner (Fig 1C and 1D)
                      (P < 0.0001 for all doses examined). The IC50for the transformation inhibitory activity of 
                      GLSF and GLS was estimated at 0.0085 and 0.0075 mg/mL, respectively. Thus, GLSF and GLS 
                      inhibited epidermal malignant transformation at non-toxic concentrations. Since transforma- 
                      tion of JB6 P+ is an assay predictive for in vivo cancer preventive activity [18], these data sug- 
                      gest that GL products, both GLSF and GLS, are able to prevent skin cancer.


PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0265615 March 21, 2022 5 / 18

